"The Best Poop Position
for Constipation"
In my last poop video, I talked
about the potential efficacy
of prunes and dried figs in
helping to keep us regular.
What about the influence of
body position on defecation?
While squatting continues
to be the traditional position
in populations of Asia and Africa,
Westerners have become
accustomed to sitting on toilet
seats. And when we do that,
when we sit upright,
our poop is forced to make
a nearly 90-degree turn,
the so-called recto-anal angle.
Now, that's a good
thing in terms of
keeping us from pooping our
pants every time we sit down.
But when it comes to doing our
business, the sitting toilet posture
defeats the purpose of our
body's brilliant design—
like trying to drive a car without
releasing the parking brake.
Yet many physicians
are hesitant to discuss
such an unmentionable bodily
function or may just be ignorant.
Doctors don't know squat.
Of course, this is coming from
someone who owns a company
selling people squatting
platforms for their toilets.
In a previous video, I talked about
those little footstools you can use
to raise your knees when you
assume the pooping position,
but they were not found to
make a difference in terms
of self-described
difficulty in defecating
or the average time spent
emptying one's bowels.
But those stools give only
a measly 4-inch boost.
The so-called Squatty Potty
is twice that height,
and while you have to
admire their graphics,
from booty blockage to fecal fiesta,
complete with little rainbow poops,
it had never been put
to the test until now.
The Implementation of
a Defecation Posture
Modification Device, i.e.,
Squatty Potty, and it worked!
Increased feelings of bowel
emptiness, reduced straining,
and about a minute off of
their on-the-pot reading time.
The only downside
is the discomfort.
Even just a 6-inch riser was found
to cause such extreme discomfort
in research subjects
in a previous trial,
they'd abandoned even
trying to study it.
How else could we get that
same change in angle you get
from raising your feet?
How about just tipping forward?
Look familiar? It's like that famous
sculpture by Rodin, The Thinker.
And indeed, Cleveland Clinic
researchers set out to study
"The Thinker" position for
defecation, and were able to show
an opening of the ano-rectal
angle, as measured using
cinedefecography—your
S.A.T. word for the day,
meaning basically
x-ray poop movie—
opening to more than 130
degrees, better than what
you can get just raising your feet,
which is only around 90 degrees.
So "The Thinker" position may be a
more efficient method for defecation.
and may help with constipation,
but it has not yet been
formally put to the test.
As an aside, you can imagine
how the worst position might be
flat on your back using a bedpan,
because the spike in blood pressure
in your heart and brain when
you bear down, straining at stool,
is associated with sudden death
from heart attack and stroke.
In fact, it's been found to be the
most common activity of daily living
being performed at the
time of death in Japan.
And those who can't get out of bed
would seem to be especially at risk.
That's why, if at all possible,
it can help to sit people up in bed
to cause less strain on the system.
It's important to take a step back,
though, in this sitting vs. squatting
debate as this commentary
did nearly 50 years ago.
Yes, the squatting position is
said to be natural, since it's used
by so-called primitive peoples
who pass large stools easily,
such that squatting advocates
blame the porcelain throne
on all manner of Western maladies.
But does the position
really make a difference
if you're eating the right foods?
The man who squats because he
has no modern plumbing also tends
to eat more natural foods that
haven't had the fiber processed out.
Adding fiber to the diet can enable
constipated patients to poop
effortlessly without having to squat
over some hole in the ground.
So maybe if we just change
the design of our diets,
we don't have to change
the design of our plumbing.